Guide to the John Lowenthal Papers TAM.190
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series II: Subject Files, 1942-2003
  - Trials of Alger Hiss: Zablodowsky, David, 1977, 1981; cuid8877 (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Turner, Kay: Correspondence, 1996; cuid8878 (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - Tytell, Martin: "The $7,500 Typewriter I Built for Alger Hiss" (True Magazine), Aug 1952; cuid8879 (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - United Nations: Notes and Typescript, undated, 1965; cuid8880 (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - United States Court of Appeals: USA v. Morton Sobell, 1963; cuid8881 (Box 22, Folder 9)
  - USA v. Alger Hiss: The Film Fund, 1976-1978; cuid8882 (Box 22, Folder 10)
  - USA v. Alger Hiss: National Endowment for the Humanities, 1976-1978; cuid8883 (Box 22, Folder 11)
  - USA v. Alger Hiss: The Television Laboratory, 1976-1978; cuid8884 (Box 22, Folder 12)
  - United States Department of Agriculture: Agricultural Adjustment Administration, 1935; cuid8885 (Box 22, Folder 13)
  - Van der Heuvel, Katrina, 1992-1995; cuid8886 (Box 22, Folder 14)
  - Vassiliev, Alexander v. Frank Cass and Co., 2001-2002; cuid8887 (Box 22, Folder 15)
  - Vassiliev, Alexander v. Frank Cass and Co., 2003; cuid8888 (Box 22, Folder 16)
  - Venona, 1990s; cuid8889 (Box 22, Folder 17)
  - Venona: "Ales" Awarded Soviet Decoration, 1953, 2000; cuid8890 (Box 22, Folder 18)
  - Venona Article: Correspondence, 1999; cuid8891 (Box 22, Folder 19)
  - Venona Article: Draft, 1999-2000; cuid8892 (Box 22, Folder 20)
  - Venona Article: Mailing Lists and Public Relations, 2000-2002; cuid8893 (Box 22, Folder 21)
  - Venona Article: Notes, re:, 2000-2002; cuid8894 (Box 22, Folder 22)
  - Venona Article: Referees, 2002; cuid8895 (Box 22, Folder 23)
  - Venona Article: Responses, 2002-2003; cuid8896 (Box 22, Folder 24)
  - Venona: Bykov, Boris, 1996-1999; cuid8897 (Box 22, Folder 25)
  - Venona Conference, Oct 3, 1996-Oct 4, 1996; cuid8898 (Box 22, Folder 26)
  - Vinnedge, Harlan: Correspondence, 1973-1974; cuid8899 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Vinnedge, Harlan: "A Second Look at the Hiss Case," Typescript, undated; cuid8900 (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Visson, Lynn: Handwritten Notes, re:, Dec 1992; cuid8901 (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Von Mehren, Robert: Correspondence, 1975, 1993; cuid8902 (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Vyshinsky, Andrei Y: Handwritten Notes, re:, 1996, 2002; cuid8903 (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - W. H. Lowdermilk and Company: HUAC Reprints, re:, May 1962; cuid8904 (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - Wadleigh, Henry Julian, 1948-1950, 1977, 1994; cuid8905 (Box 23, Folder 7)
  - Washington Post: Correspondence, 1992-1993; cuid8906 (Box 23, Folder 8)
  - Website: The Alger Hiss Story, 2000-2001; cuid8907 (Box 23, Folder 9)
  - Website: The Alger Hiss Story, Zip Disc, Nov 11, 2000; cuid8908 (Box 23, Folder 10)
  - Weinstein, Allen, 1970-1999; cuid8909 (Box 23, Folder 11)
  - Weinstein, Allen: The Haunted Wood, re:, 1990s; cuid8910 (Box 23, Folder 12)
  - Weinstein, Allen: Perjury, Re:, 1970s; cuid8911 (Box 23, Folder 13)
  - Welles, Summer: Handwritten Notes, re:, Feb 12, 1949; cuid8912 (Box 23, Folder 14)
  - Were Oppenheimer, Sobell and Hiss Spies?: Typescript and Notes, 1994; cuid8913 (Box 23, Folder 15)
  - Weyl, Nathaniel, undated, 1952, 1976-1999; cuid8914 (Box 23, Folder 16)
  - Whitemore, Hugh: American Playhouse, "Concealed Enemies: The Hiss/Chambers Spy Case", 1984; cuid8915 (Box 23, Folder 17)
  - Whitemore, Hugh: Thames Television, "Alger Hiss Project," First of Three Films, Typescript, undated; cuid8916 (Box 23, Folder 18)
  - Whitemore, Hugh: Thames Television, "Concealed Enemies: The Hiss/Chambers Spy Case, Part 1 Accusation," Revised Draft, undated; cuid8917 (Box 23, Folder 19)
  - Whitemore, Hugh: Thames Television, "Concealed Enemies: The Hiss/Chambers Spy Case, Part 2 Confession," First Draft, undated; cuid8918 (Box 23, Folder 20)
  - Whitemore, Hugh: Thames Television, "Concealed Enemies: The Hiss/Chambers Spy Case, Parts 1 and 2," Revisions, Jul 1983; cuid8919 (Box 23, Folder 21)
  - Whitemore, Hugh: Thames Television, "Concealed Enemies: The Hiss/Chambers Spy Case, Part 3 Investigation," Revisions, 1983; cuid8920 (Box 23, Folder 22)
  - Whitemore, Hugh: "The Trials of Alger Hiss," Treatment, 1980; cuid8921 (Box 23, Folder 23)
  - Why Ales Cannot Be Alger Hiss (JL): Typescript, 1996; cuid8922 (Box 23, Folder 24)
  - Wiener, John: "Compromised Positions" (The Nation), Jan 1993-Feb 1993; cuid8923 (Box 23, Folder 25)
  - Wiener, John: Re: "Pumpkin Papers", 1990, 1996-1998; cuid8924 (Box 23, Folder 26)
  - Wines, Michael: Correspondence, 1992; cuid8925 (Box 23, Folder 27)
  - Wood, Sally: Correspondence, Feb 3, 1950; cuid8926 (Box 23, Folder 28)
  - Woodrow Wilson Center for Cold War History: Handwritten Notes re: Hiss, 1992-1993, 2003; cuid8927 (Box 23, Folder 29)
  - Worth, Joan: Correspondence, 1993; cuid8928 (Box 23, Folder 30)
  - Wright, Charles A.: Writings, 1952, 1973, 2000; cuid8929 (Box 23, Folder 31)
  - Younger, Irving: Re: Hiss, 1970s; cuid8930 (Box 23, Folder 32)
  - Zubok, Vladislav, 1993; cuid8931 (Box 23, Folder 33)
- Series III: Alger Hiss Production Files, 1938-1991
  - Associated Press Photograph Description, undated; cuid8932 (Box 34, Folder 1)
  - Cartoons, undated; cuid8933 (Box 34, Folder 2)
  - Cartoons (Oversize), undated; cuid8934 (Box Shared Tamiment OS003, Folder 1)
  - Chambers, Esther, 1948-1962; cuid8935 (Box 34, Folder 3)
  - Chambers, Whittaker, 1948-1950; cuid8936 (Box 34, Folder 4)
  - Chambers at Farm, 1949-1953; cuid8937 (Box 34, Folder 5)
  - Chambers' Farm and Pumpkins, 1948, undated; cuid8938 (Box 34, Folder 6)
  - Chambers with Stripling, Nixon and Bentley, 1951; cuid8939 (Box 34, Folder 7)
  - Chambers at HUAC, undated; cuid8940 (Box 34, Folder 8)
  - Collins and Hiss, undated; cuid8941 (Box 34, Folder data_value_missing_59fe5b69f198012634f73edb14ed21fc)
  - Daily News (Negatives and Photocopies), 1934-1961; cuid8942 (Box 34, Folder 10)
  - [Damaged Negatives], undated; cuid8943 (Box 34, Folder 11)
  - Documents, 1938-1957; cuid8944 (Box 34, Folder 12)
  - Donald Hiss (Includes Alger Hiss), 1948; cuid8945 (Box 34, Folder 13)
  - Hiss, Alger: LIFE (Photocopies), undated; cuid8946 (Box 34, Folder 14)
  - Hiss: Alone, 1948-1950; cuid8947 (Box 34, Folder 15)
  - Hiss: at HUAC, 1948-1961; cuid8948 (Box 34, Folder 16)
  - Hiss: NYE Committee / San Francisco Conference / YALTA, 1945; cuid8949 (Box 34, Folder 17)
  - Hiss: Personal - Familly and Friends, 1951-1975; cuid8950 (Box 34, Folder 18)
  - Hiss: Portraits, undated; cuid8951 (Box 34, Folder 19)
  - Hiss: Prison, Mug Shot, Handcuffs, Post-Prison Press Conferences, 1946-1956; cuid8952 (Box 34, Folder 20)
  - Hiss: Stationary Office, Massachussets Bar, 1967-1976; cuid8953 (Box 34, Folder 21)
  - Hiss: with Priscilla, Tony Alone, 1949-1959; cuid8954 (Box 34, Folder 22)
  - HUAC: Long Shots, CU Stripling, Mundt, Thomas Guarding Pumpkin Papers, 1943-1948; cuid8955 (Box 34, Folder 23)
  - Index of Tabbed Photographs, undated; cuid8956 (Box 34, Folder 24)
  - Judges Kaufman and Goddard, 1949-1950; cuid8957 (Box 34, Folder 25)
  - Juries: 1st and 2nd, 1948-1950; cuid8958 (Box 34, Folder 26)
  - Lawyers: Corss, Stryker, Rosenwald, McLean, Shapero, 1949, undated; cuid8959 (Box 34, Folder 27)
  - Lowenthal, John Portraits and Contract Sheets, 1980-1981; undated; cuid8960 (Box 34, Folder 28)
  - Miscellaneous (Great Depression), undated; cuid8961 (Box 34, Folder 29)
  - Miscellaneous (Includes Paul Robeson, Communities, Spanish Civil War), 1948-1962; cuid8962 (Box 34, Folder 30)
  - Miscellaneous Dupicate and Promotional Photographs, 1980-1991, undated; cuid8963 (Box 34, Folder 31)
  - Miscellaneous Promotional Photographs, 1948-1951; cuid8964 (Box 34, Folder 32)
  - Mundt / "Hiss Guilty" Headline, 1948; cuid8965 (Box 34, Folder 33)
  - Murphy, Thomas F., 1950-1951; cuid8966 (Box 34, Folder 34)
  - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, 1949-1977; cuid8967 (Box 34, Folder 35)
  - Nixon, 1948-1955; cuid8968 (Box 34, Folder 36)
  - Original Photographs, undated; cuid8969 (Box 34, Folder 37)
  - Oversize, 1953-1979; undated; cuid8970 (Box Shared Tamiment OS003, Folder 2)
  - Personalities, 1931-1969; cuid8971 (Box 34, Folder 38)
  - Photos Used in Final Cut, 1948-1952; cuid8972 (Box 34, Folder 39)
  - Press Stills, 1955-1970; undated; cuid8973 (Box 34, Folder 40)
  - Pulled for Possible Promotion (Hiss on Trial), 1948-1955; cuid8974 (Box 34, Folder 41)
  - Shoot Rehearsed Movement (Whittaker Chambers, Alger Hiss, Henry Julian Wadleigh), 1943-1951; cuid8975 (Box 34, Folder 42)
  - Shoot - Straight (Whittaker Chambers, Robert Stripling, Sumner Welles), 1948-1950; cuid8976 (Box 34, Folder 43)
  - Stripling and Wheeler, 1944-1948; cuid8977 (Box 34, Folder 44)
  - Swish to Left on Mach (Oliver Edmond Clubb and Whittaker Chambers), 1951, undated; cuid8978 (Box 34, Folder data_value_missing_cb7413ad1b839effcf712f43d3b38864)
- Series IV: Addendum, 1949-1993
  This unprocessed box (1 linear foot) of material is not available for research, pending its reorganization, description, and completion of basic preservation measures.
  - Agnese Nelms Haury Trust / Emil W. Haury Graduate Fellowship Fund, 1991-1992; cuid8979 (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Gray Panthers [2 posters], 1982; undated; cuid8980 (Box Shared Tamiment MSXOS002, Folder 1)
  - Lowenthal, Anne [Professor]: Correspondence, 1976, 1979; cuid8981 (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Lowenthal, John: Correspondence, 1954-1960; cuid8982 (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Lowenthal, John: Correspondence, 1971-1993; cuid8983 (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Lowenthal, John: Letter to "Mother", undated; cuid8984 (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Lowenthal, John: Letter to Mr. and Mrs. John Wolf [from Paris], Aug 15, 1949; cuid8985 (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - Lowenthal, John: Letters to Lowenthal Family [from Paris], Jul 1949-Sep 1949; cuid8986 (Box 24, Folder 7)
  - "More on Whittaker Chambers and NYPL" (Research Libraries Bulletin; vol. 5, no. 3), 1993; cuid8987 (Box 24, Folder 8)
  - "The Trials of Algiers Hiss" (92nd St Y) [poster], [1980]; cuid8988 (Flat-file-folder 2)
  - The Trials of Alger Hiss [Film brochure], c. 1980; cuid8989 (Box 24, Folder 9)
  - "The Trials of Algiers Hiss"(London Film Festival) [poster], 1980; cuid8990 (Box Shared Tamiment MSXOS002, Folder 1)
  - "The Trials of Algiers Hiss" [poster], [1980]; cuid8991 (Flat-file-folder 2)
  - U.S. Troops Out Now [poster], undated; cuid8992 (Box Shared Tamiment MSXOS002, Folder 1)
  - "Vindication for Alger Hiss" (Rochester Chronicle), Nov 18, 1992; cuid8993 (Box 24, Folder 10)
  - David Levine caricature of Alger Hiss and Richard Nixon, 1975; cuid8995 (Box Shared Tamiment 011, Folder 2)
- Series V: 2020 Accretion, 1978-2009
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of correspondence, notes, legal documents, and subject files concerning the 2002 libel trial of Alexander Vassiliev and historical scholarship on the Alger Hiss perjury trials. Some of the materials in this series are created by David Lowenthal after John Lowenthal's death.
  - "Academic Freedom: The Hiss Case Yields a Noteworthy Victory" by David Lowenthal, 2004 (Box 36, Folder 1)
  - "Alger Hiss: The Perfect Victim" by John Lowenthal, 1997-2003 (Box 36, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 2004-2005 (Box 36, Folder 3)
  - Eduard Mark, 1978-2005 (Box 36, Folder 4-5)
  - The Trials of Alger Hiss, 1981-1982 (Box 36, Folder 6)
  - Alexander Vassiliev -- General, 2003-2009 (Box 36, Folder 7-11)
  - Alexander Vassiliev -- "Black Notebook" with Translated Notes from KGB Archival Records, after 2007; cuid34464 (E-records Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_190_ER_1)
  - Alexander Vassiliev -- Jury Bundle, 1992-2003 (Box 36, Folder 12-13, Box 37, Folder 1-3)
  - Allen Weinstein, 2003-2005 (Box 37, Folder 4)
- Series VI: Unprocessed Materials, Undated
  - "Libyan Technical Assistance - "International Conciliation", 1957-05-02; cuid8996 (Reel 38, Reel cuid8996, E-records tamwag_tam190, E-records cuid8996)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Format: 1/4" open reel audio, Duration: 30 min.
  - Film, "Chip Lockwood, et al", 1965-01-29; cuid8997 (Box Shared Tamiment 013, Reel 2, Box 34, Folder 46)
  - Unmarked film, undated; cuid8998 (Box Shared Tamiment 013, Reel 3)
  - Candid portrait, undated; cuid8999 (Box Shared Tamiment 011, Folder 14)